5th November 2009

Previous release revision:

This release revision: 1266

Steps To Take for Update

In order…

Run database update tasks:

rake db:sessions:clear RAILS_ENV=production
rake db:migrate RAILS_ENV=production

Restart memcached server(s)

Run latest update scripts:

ruby script/biocatalogue/update_activity_logs_aug09.rb
ruby script/biocatalogue/update_providers_sep09.rb
ruby script/biocatalogue/update_soaplab_sep09.rb -e production

Update config/initializers/biocat_local.rb with new settings

Including new RPX settings

Make sure the Solr schema.xml file is updated

Restart Solr service(s)

Reindex the search engine:

rake solr:reindex RAILS_ENV=production --trace

Restart the worker(s). For each, do:

ruby script/worker stop
ruby script/worker start

Delete public/stats.html

Update the search query suggestions list:

rake biocatalogue:submit:update_search_query_suggestions RAILS_ENV=production

Rebuild assets

rake asset:packager:build_all

Restart application instance(s)

Release Notes

Email sent to the friends list on 6th Nov 09:

Hi all,

After our successful public beta launch at ISMB 09 we've been working hard on improving the BioCatalogue. We've recently updated the BioCatalogue live site (http://www.biocatalogue.org) with the following:

- Improved WSDL parsing with the ability to parse and store information on complex types of SOAP inputs and outputs (including complex types defined in external schema files).
- New user interface for viewing the information on complex types of SOAP inputs and outputs.
- Significant performance improvements to search, the service index and filtering.
- New user interface for quickly adding annotations (when signed in).
- Support for OpenID, Google, Yahoo, Twitter and Facebook accounts. At the moment you can only link one of these external accounts with your BioCatalogue account (or open a new BioCatalogue account with one of these accounts).
- Simple/detailed service listings views for the search results and service index.
- More help text and guidance for Soaplab services.
- Better user interface for viewing example data annotations.
- Better user interface for filtering by service categories.
- Revamped user sign in, sign up and edit profile pages.
- Many more user interface tweaks and bug fixes.
- More work on our underlying infrastructure and systems.

Please note that we have also updated our Terms of Use (http://www.biocatalogue.org/termsofuse) in which we:
- Make a clear distinction between Members and Users of the BioCatalogue.
- Clarify the definitions of the key terms used.
- Clarify our policies regarding content and the BioCatalogue website and services.
- Clarify our data preservation policy.
- Outline our take down / withdrawal policy.

To find out what we will be working on for the rest of the year and next year please see: <http://www.biocatalogue.org/wiki/doku.php?id=public:roadmap#fourth_quarter_2009_oct_-_dec>

We also have a pre-alpha REST API to access the content of the BioCatalogue that we are testing at the moment. If you are interested in getting involved with this, please contact Jiten Bhagat <jits@cs.man.ac.uk>. We are hoping to release the initial version of the API before the end of the year.

As always, we value your feedback, ideas and discussion, so please feel free to get in touch with us with your thoughts.

Regards,
The BioCatalogue Team

Date: Monday 07th June 2010

Time: 15:00-16:00 (UK)

Telcon No: 08444737630

Pin: 70503011

Attending

Manchester: Franck, Jits, Mannie

EBI: Eric, Hamish

Apologies

Agenda

Actions from the last telecom

Progress report

Review of Monitoring

Review of Curation

Service update checker

Publicity/outreach

EMBRACE service provider workshop - feedback from Hamish

Franck presenting the Function Unit paper at IEEE

Jits- BioCatalogue demo at ISMB 2010

Technical meeting

Summary of tasks on Rubyforge

BioCatalogue support review

20 Questions analysis

Actions from Previous Meeting

Eric to write down his latest idea about monitoring ongoing

Jits/Mannie: Write API and Mass curation tool via spreadsheets ongoing

Upcoming Meetings

AOB

Minutes

Review of Monitoring:

-How best can we monitor web service enpoints? The current approach assumes that a service endpoint is fine if it returns a 'xml' or 'html' page when it's pinged. That doesn't seem to be the case for some services.(e.g. DDBJ). We probably need to tune the monitoring test according to the service.
-During the Embrace workshop 2 different ways of monitoring came across: in the first instance, monitor services with a redirect wsdl location, in this case the agreement is that we should automatically pick the new location; in the second instance, when a wsdl changes(e.g functional changes) but the previous version is still working the agreement is that we should keep both copies but point to the latest.

Review of curation:

-Franck is clearing up the registry and archiving deprecated services.
-Jits has started to work on the curation dashboard. Currently curators can identify which operation within a service are similar based on their name. Annotation can be copied across from operation to operation.

Report from the Embrace service provider meeting:

-The general feedback is that the BioCatalogue is a good product and very useful too.
-Need to support semantic annotation using EDAM for example; Jon is writing down how this can be achieved.
-Need to support SAWSDL and BioSXD. There is growing number of services providers supporting BioXSD
-Find better rating of the service. A metric for service provider to see how their service is being used.
-Possibility to view more services per page (at the moment too much scrolling when using a laptop.
-Reduce white space
-Atom feed with category for service providers

New actions

Eric to send around a mail about endpoint monitoring

Previous meeting: Phone Conference Meeting on May 17 2010

Next meeting: Phone Conference Meeting on June 14 2010

Meeting Agenda/Minutes

Date: Friday 1st August 2008

Time: 15:00-17:00 (UK)

Attending

Manchester: Carole, Katy, Franck, Jits

EBI: Eric, Hamish, Thomas

Apologies

Rodrigo (@ conference in Colombia)

Minuting

Jits

Agenda

[CANCELLED due to sickness] Guiseppe's talk ERGOT: combining DHTs and SONs for Semantic Based Service Discovery (will need video skype at the EBI). He is keen to present this to the BioCatalogue team before he leaves his placement with us.

Action Items from previous meeting

Communications

Review of requirements for first pilot, and deadline for pilot features spec.

Relationship and overlaps with myExperiment of first pilot - discuss the proposed pilot architecture.

Planning of first pilot development and content

De briefing of ISMB

Review of focus group Pals liaison

Scheduling and location of the next face to face meeting. I had suggested we meet at the e-Science All Hands meeting in Edinburgh.

Scheduling and location of hackathon.

Schedule for the Advisory Board (which Carole would not recommend until we have sorted out differences)

Actions from Previous Meeting

Action EBI : Suggest dates for the face-2-face meeting at EBI

Action Franck : Send flyer and questionnaire to the mailing list before EBI team flies to ISMB on Friday

Action Eric/Franck : Agree on database model for the pilot

Action Thomas : Create individual wiki accounts for the Manchester team

Minutes

Previous Actions

All actions tackled.

Communications

EBI folk need to be kept up to date with myExperiment - they need more information about how it works, how it affects BioCatalogue, what the future, vision and so on is.

Carole: we need face to face, whiteboards, watercooler meetings!!

Everyone agrees that we need to meet face to face soon - so meet @ EBI on Thu 14th and Fri 15th Aug (Jits stays on Mon and Tue as well). This is mainly a designathon and bit of a hackathon.

We need to use the wiki more. Especially to document ad hoc communications via skype, voice and so on.

Pilot (for October)

Carole: need substantial work on requirements doc before F2F meeting.

We should all work on this before next meeting.

Carole: need a highly synergistic implementation between BioCatalogue and myExperiment. Very important not to duplicate effort and code.

After F2F meeting:

Content requirements

Design document of the system

Beginnings of code

Clear and unambiguous definitions and documentation on requirements, what components to use, what is 'in' myExperiment, what is 'in' BioCatalogue, a plan and so on.

Some information on expected performance, scalability, support and so on for the pilot.

We should be able to source services from places we already know, e.g: EMBRACE (must), FETA (should).

Carole: suggest we use the MoSCoW (Must Should Coulud Wont) requirements classification method for the requirements doc.

Could have a hackathon 27th - 28th Aug in Southampton just before myExp management meeting (29th Aug)? YES - Eric, Thomas and Jits, in Southampton.

Do a review at AHM (2nd week of Sept).

ISMB debrief + PALs/Friends liason planning

Very successful for all!

Questionnaires should be put on wiki and analysed.

We need to contact people interested and get them on the BioCatalogue-Friends mailing list. Use as the PALs mailing list. Mention that we have the meeting on the 14th and that now is the time to get requirements in.

Had a gathering, mainly with some NBIC people. They came up with a set of things they would like to see in an early catalogue. Simple stuff. They would like to be part of the friends/PALs set up. They particularly would like to “newsfeed” information about their services/systems to us - we become an aggregator.

Hamish: based around exporting the quality score and other metrics (eg: percentage uptime).

Franck: will be the Friends Handler!

New Actions

ALL: work on requirements document before next week's meeting

ALL: plan agenda etc for big F2F meeting on 14th Aug.

Jits: get documentation together for EBI folks.

Franck & Eric: put questionnaires + results + analysis on wiki.

Franck: contact interested parties and get them on BioCatalogue-Friends and get them involved.

Next Meeting

Friday 8th August 2008 @ 14:00 - 16:00

Upcoming Meetings

F2F: 14th Aug - 15th Aug 2008 @ EBI, Cambridge.

Hackathon: 27th - 28th Aug 2008 @ Southampton.

e-Science All Hands Meeting (2nd week of Sept).

Previous/Next Meetings

Previous meeting: Phone Conference Meeting on Jul 15 2008

Next meeting: Phone Conference Meeting on Aug 08 2008

The Revised BioCatalogue Roadmap for 2010

Please note that the time scales listed are estimated. New requirements and changes driven by the user community may affect features, delivery dates and schedule. You can access the BioCatalogue 2009 roadmap here: 2009 roadmap

First quarter of 2010 (Jan - Mar)

Public APIs (I) - Basic RESTful APIs to BioCatalogue (mainly read).

Final merge of the EMBRACE registry.

Service monitoring - testing - Test scripts to test out service functionality can be provided by submitters and service providers. We will then run these regularly to provide us with metrics on the availability/reliability. A traffic light system (red, green, amber) gives users an at-a-glance view on status.

REST services support (II) - Better support for REST services, with the ability to describe and annotate the exact Resources, Methods, Parameters and Representations of REST services.

Service changes monitoring - Monitoring changes in the WSDLs of services and updating the BioCatalogue records and providing a log of changes.

UI improvements - A revamped operations/inputs/outputs browser.

Integration with myExperiment (I) - Services from BioCatalogue displayed in myExperiment so users of myExperiment can browse them. Also, workflows in myExperiment will have links to the relevant services, with metadata and monitoring status pulled from BioCatalogue.

Richer user profiles - Ability to harvest your profile information from myExperiment.

Content curation - Improvement of the quality of the content of the catalogue.

Outreach -

Second quarter of 2010 (Apr - Jun)

Better service filtering and ranking - Ability to filter or rank service based on annotations, quality, curators etc.

Service ownership - Better management of who the provides a service and which people are maintainers / points of contacts.

Public APIs (II) - More functional RESTful APIs to BioCatalogue (read and write).

Content curation - Content quality improvement

Annotation status bar - A status bar to display the overall annotation status of a service. The bar will take into account the description of the service, the description of its operations, inputs/outputs, example values etc.

myBioCatalogue - Ability to set up your own local BioCatalogue registry.

Third quarter 2010 (Jul - Sep)

Advanced search functionality (II) - Similarity searches. Semantic search: search for services using terms from a defined ontology. Amazon-like search: people who searched for these also searched for those.

Integration with myExperiment (II) - linking to (or displaying parts of) workflows from myExperiment that contain a service/operation in the BioCatalogue. Also, mining service connections from workflows in myExperiment.

Service mirrors - Support for having mirrors (i.e.: many deployments of a service).

Annotation Jamboree! (II) - ISMB '10 or EBI Cambridge

Curation workbench/tools - New curation tools designed for expert curators.

Better annotation and curation features (II) - Curation reports, Curation assertions and more improvements for expert/community curators as well as casual annotators.

Integration with Taverna - Ability to import Web Services and annotations to and from BioCatalogue and Taverna.

Fourth quarter 2010 (Oct - Dec)

“Try it now” service functionality - Ability to test and play with a service within the BioCatalogue interface before using it.

Semantic annotation support - Ability to annotate service using ontologies and controlled vocabularies (possibly import/export semantically annotated services in different formats such as SAWSDL, SA-REST).

Notifications and news feeds per service - RSS/ATOM feeds for services, providing information on all activity on a service within the BioCatalogue.

Better service availability reports - Including filtering by service availability and “at-a-glance” summary reports for curators.

Curator stamp - Members who contribute a lot to the curation of services in the BioCatalogue will have a curator badge display next to their name.

Content curation - Content quality improvement

Service versions - Support for different versions of a service (i.e.: SOAP and REST versions of a single service).

Functional Units of Services- Ability to present services in terms of their biological functions, biological data types and biological resources.

Content acquisition (III) - Better support for BioMoby and SADI services. Scavenge services from ProgrammableWeb and SeekDa.

The pilot....

Covers SOAP services from: DDBJ, EBI, NCBI and community providers such as BioMOBY, myGrid, EMBRACE and BioSapiens and relevant services sourced from SeekDa!. Work on support for DAS and REST services is in progress.

After the Pilot

Integration with myExperiment

Services from BioCatalogue displayed in myExperiment so users of myExperiment can browse them. This includes a “Latest Services” and “Updated Services” list.

Services within workflows in myExperiment reference the appropriate services in BioCatalogue so users can click through to the information in BioCatalogue.

Integration to Taverna

Ability to import Web Services and annotations to and from BioCatalogue and Taverna.

myBioCatalogue

Setup your private BioCatalogue for your project or organisation

For the list of complete features after the pilot see our Roadmap

More about the features

Precious metals

The BioCatalogue Pilot focuses on the simplest possible search, curation and submission in order to encourage use and to lower barriers of engagement. The emphasis is on wide service coverage. Search will be through keywords; curation through keyword tagging and tags generated from automated analysis of service description documents and submission by simple provision of a URL and optional metadata. The Basic BioCatalogue Pilot will cater for SOAP-based and REST Web Services, that said it will cover over a lot of services, including those from the EMBL-EBI, NCBI, DDBJ and those from many collaborators. We have defined a data model for service annotation with four levels of compliance; from the bronze (basic level) through silver and gold to the very best high quality and comprehensive platinum. Simple service monitoring for operational metrics will be in place.

Machines

We have established the domain and hardware infrastructure at the EMBL-EBI. Several web nodes have been allocated that will provide the biocatalogue with redundancy in the service as well as fail-over capabilities. We have also clarified our technology choices, for rapid development we are using Ruby On Rails 2 and mySQL, and reusing components from myExperiment; The choice of Ruby on Rails eases the development of the REST API and a highly usable front end. It encourages the development of reusable components which can easily be assembled, all through a simple yet highly functional model driven architecture. We have defined the architecture of the BioCatalogue, and specifically that of the Basic BioCatalogue Pilot.

Data model

We have defined a first cut data model for service annotation that can be incrementally enriched. Identified six classes of metadata: service function, operation, operational metrics, community standing, service provenance, and conditions of use. The data model also takes into account handling of versions of services during their life-cycle, as well as tracking individual deployments or instances of the service that may possess their own data metrics or parameters, operational characteristics and metadata. biocatalogue_data_model.ppt

About service submission

A simple service provider submission system is in place in the pilot of BioCatalogue. It should take no more than a few seconds to submit a service and automatically annotate it to bronze standard. The basic information includes: name of submitter, email, provider name, hosting institution, name of service, location and exposure of the methods/actions described within it. The methods of a service will be parsed automatically from the WSDL and fed into the data store where they become searchable via the portals’ search engine. Batch submission of service will also be available to cater for service provider such as SOAPLAB (http://www.ebi.ac.uk/soaplab) and incoming data feeds from collaborators such as SeekDA (http://www.seekda.com)

Searching for services

We are using Solr (apache.solr.org), which is based on the Lucene full-text search library (apache.lucene.org), and for which there is significant expertise build up within the group. The search interface is modelled around myExperiment.org; . A strong commonality between these projects will lead to an easier and more obvious use of the results by the users.

The BioCatalogue will feed other search engines such as Google and the EB-eye with data. This will be possible by using the RSS/Atom or RDF feeds, which are planned to allow registered and non-registered users to stay tuned to BioCatalogue activities. The BioCatalogue pilot already provides support for OpenSearch (http://www.opensearch.org) for browsers that use the technology. This will allow users to query the BioCatalogue in a semi-independent fashion from the portal.